Guide to the Robert College records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert College Records,
1858-1986
Robert College (Istanbul, Turkey)
89 linear ft. (207 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6607719
These records contain information related to the formation of Robert College (Bebek, Turkey). They document the founders' attempts to define the mission of a Christian college within the Ottoman Empire, their efforts to obtain permission to purchase land, and their efforts to gain necessary permits to build upon the site.
Historical Note
Robert College, the first American-sponsored college founded outside the United States, opened its doors in Bebek, Turkey, in 1863 with four students. The following year the American trustees obtained papers of incorporation in the State of New York allowing the! institution to raise funds in support of the experiment. The college was an outgrowth of American missionary efforts within the Ottoman Empire, but had no formal connection with the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. Under the leadership of the Reverend Cyrus Hamlin, a Congregational minister, who had spent many years in Turkey, and with the support of Christopher R. Robert, a prosperous New York merchant, the college gradually became recognized as an important institution for educating the Christian minorities within the Ottoman Empire.
Cyrus Hamlin's desire to establish a permanent campus increasingly diverted his energies from administrative duties. After protracted I negotiations and considerable resistance from the Turkish authorities, he secured a site above the fortress of Rumeli Hisar overlooking the Bosphorus and began personally to oversee I construction of the new building. In the process he became increasingly alienated from his colleagues and as a consequence the trustees shifted responsibility for administering the college to George Washburn, a long time resident of Turkey who had served as I treasurer for the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions before joining the Robert College faculty.
In 1871 the college moved to its new campus and while the number of students grew so did the tension between Hamlin and the faculty. In 1877 the trustees officially named Washburn president though in fact he had been acting as such for some years. During his long tenure Washburn gradually assembled a faculty of distinguished scholars who firmly established the college's academic reputation. These professors were augmented by tutors from the United States and by local academics.
With the death of Christopher Robert in 1878, the college lost one of its leaders and its chief benefactor. However, his generous bequest laid the basis for an endowment. That same year the college's first catalog was published showing that since 1863, 912 students of many nationalities had attended and 76 had graduated. The number of students grew markedly during the l880s but in the process the physical plant and equipment gradually became outmoded. I Faculty morale declined. In the United States a new group of trustees was recruited, and men such as John S. Kennedy, Cleveland H. Dodge and William Sloane inspired an ambitious building program II that both expanded and revitalized the college. In 1903 Dr. Caleb Gates succeeded George Washburn as president. During his twenty-nine year administration the student body underwent a dramatic transformation as the Young Turk movement led to an Ii unprecedented demand for education along western lines. "Concurrently, government relaxation of barriers against attending foreign schools encouraged the enrollment of Turkish youngsters in t1 existing institutions such as Robert College
In 1912 the School of Engineering was established, a major step in harmony with the needs of a Turkey determined to modernize itself and provide technical education to its young generation.
With the coming of World War I, Robert College faced a host of ;I pressures and experienced severe shortages of supplies. II Nevertheless, the college continued to fulfill its educational mission. Even after the United States entered the war and severed diplomatic relations with Turkey, Robert College never was obliged to close its doors. A significant indication of the relationship I between the two countries is the fact that there was no declaration of hostilities despite the fact that Turkey was allied with the Central Powers.
At the end of the war the rising spirit of Turkish nationalism left the fate of an American institution precarious. However, by the I 1920s Robert College had been in existence for over half a century and had won the respect of Turkish leaders who recognized the i crucial role of education to the process of modernization. Moreover, the United States government had never over the years EJ become associated in the public's mind with efforts to dismember the Ottoman Empire. Finally, President Woodrow Wilson's emphasis on self-determination of nations was in accord with Turkish desires for independence in the wake of World War I.
During the 1920s a militantly nationalist Turkish government sought fl to exercise increased control over all schools through its Ministry II of Education. While this thrust was not in accord with American traditions of institutional autonomy, both the government and then college maintained a degree of flexibility over the years that made it possible for generations of Turkish students to become educated in the Western liberal tradition and thereby contribute to the development of modern Turkey. This can be attributed, in some measure, to a respect for the secular traditions of the West on the part of Kemal Ataturk.
The retirement of President Caleb Gates in 1932 closed a twenty-nine year chapter in the history of the college. By that time the impact of the worldwide economic depression had severely strained the institution's finances. The trustees appointed Dr. Paul Monroe of Teachers College, Columbia University, to consolidate the college in the face of its reduced income. One of his first moves was the merger of Robert College with the American College for Girls (ACG) under a single president, though the two institutions continued for I many years to maintain their separate Boards of Trustees and their separate endowments.
Prior to the appointment of Paul Monroe in 1932 as the president of both Robert College and the Amerlcan College for Girls, the two institutions had begun sharing instructors for certain elective classes. The stringencies imposed by the depression led to further consolidation.
When ill health compelled the retirement of Dr. Monroe in 1935, he was succeeded as head of the two institutions by Dr. Walter II Livingston Wright, Jr., an Ottoman scholar whose extensive knowledge of the Near East served the colleges well during an era of profound change in Turkey. President Wright faced the continuous task of maintaining academic standards in the face of financial stringency. The curriculum underwent revision as the college strove to adapt to I the needs of a nation undergoing modernization.
As Europe's crises of the late 1930s brought war in 1939, it became increasingly difficult to attract qualified teachers. Moreover, when the U.S. became involved in 1941, President Wright was called to Washington to serve as an advisor on Near Eastern affairs. Dean Harold L. Scott, who had served Robert College in several capacities since 1911, guided the institutions through most of the war years acting as president. In 1944 Floyd Henson Black was appointed president of the college. His first teaching position had been as a tutor at Robert College in 1911. In 1914 he had returned to the United States and after completing his doctorate at Harvard he it returned in 1919 to teach Latin. In 1926 he was appointed president of the American College in Sofia where he served for the next eighteen years. By 1944, however, the war forced the closing of the college in Sofia and Floyd Black returned, this time to a combined Robert College and American College for Girls, to lead it into the postwar years. By the war's end the college was highly respected in Turkey and there was no difficulty attracting students. The problems centered on a shortage of faculty and the college's aging physical facilities. Financial constraints and an overburdened faculty threatened an erosion of academic standards, even while extracurricular activities, drama, and athletics flourished. The college found itself at a crossroads and with the impending retirement of Dr. Black in 1955, the faculty sought to re-evaluate the academic needs of the institution while the trustees undertook to seek new sources of funding.
In 1955 Dr. Duncan Ballantine, President of Reed College, was appointed by a joint presidential search committee composed of RC and ACG trustees. His mandate was to revitalize the academic programs at the college. After a year-long study sweeping changes were made. The orta, which trained eleven to fourteen-year-old youngsters, was phased out. The four-year lise was made comparable to the three-year Turkish lise and designated Robert Academy. The collegiate division was granted permission by the Turkish Government to award Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Science degrees as well as Masters degrees in both fields. The college program was reorganized into three departments, the Engineering School, the School of Business Administration, and the School of Science and Foreign Languages. All three departments were to be coeducational.
In 1958 a comparable change was made at the level of the trustees, when both Boards of Trustees and both endowments were merged under the corporate name of The Trustees of Robert College of Istanbul. This merger was ratified in 1959 by an amendment to the charter granted by the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York.
In 1961, Dr. Ballantine resigned and was succeeded in 1962 by Dr. In Patrick Murphy Malin, who had taught Economics at Swarthmore College Jj and later served as executive director of the American Civil Liberties Union. Dr. Malin presided over the centennial celebrations of the college held in 1963.
During its first century the college had fulfilled the vision of its chief founders, Christopher Robert, Cyrus Hamlin and Mary Mills Patrick, by educating successive generations of young people, beginning with the Ottoman Empire and continuing under the Turkish Republic.
Timeline:
1863 - Robert College founded by Hamlin and Robert.
1871 - American College for Girls (originally known as The Home School) founded in Gedikpasa.
1874 - American College for Girls moved to Uskudar.
1912 - Engineering school opened at Robert College (with first civil engineering program in Turkey).
1914 - American College for Girls moved to Arnavutköy campus.
1932 - Administration of RC and ACG united under leadership of a single president.
1958 - Three new schools added to the degree-granting Yuksek (Higher Education) Division of Robert College. Boards of Trustees and endowment funds of both Colleges merged under the name of the Trustees of Robert College of Istanbul.
1971 - Robert College Yüksek transferred to the Turkish Government and now carries on the Robert academic tradition as Bogaziçi University.
Robert Academy and ACG combined physically on the Arnavutköy campus as a coeducational six-year preparatory school.
Scope and Content
The records of Robert College are organized into fifteen series. Series fifteen of Robert College Records contains a vital documents series, a substantial collection of photographs, and a sizable body of records that relate to both Robert College and the American College for Girls.
The collection also contains personal papers of some of the leading figures in the history of each institution, notably Cyrus Hamlin, George Washburn, Christopher Robert, Caleb Gates, Mary Mills Patrick and Caroline Borden. Cyrus Hamlin's earliest papers date from the 1830s, while the correspondence of the correspondence Caleb Gates and Mary Patrick extends into their retirement years as they continued to remain in close touch with their colleagues and former students.
The earliest records of ACG date from 1890, the year of its founding with a charter from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The records are not as complete for the early years as for the later ones. Nevertheless, they document the pioneering role of ACG in opening higher education to women in the Near East and thereby enrich our understanding of the dramatic changes in the changes in the status of women during the twentieth century.
The collection contains a large proportion of college officials in Istanbul and the Office York. The vital role played by the trustees and material support to both colleges is well documented. Throughout the correspondence that concerns the operations of the colleges there can be found many commentaries on events in Turkey and the outlying regions of the Ottoman Empire. Moreover, the administrators of both institutions reported on their travels in Europe and the Near East. They wrote about Turkey and conditions during the Russo-Turkish conflict and both World Wars. Finally, they followed with great interest the modernization in Turkey and sought to adapt their own institutions to the far-reaching changes in Turkish society. Thus, while theses records contain the history of two American colleges, they are also significant sources for the study of modern Turkey. Accordingly, extensive descriptions of each record series are provided.
Acquisition Information: Purchased from Robert College, 2006. The collection was delivered to the Rare Book & Manuscript Library on April 12, 2007
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 parts. The first part of this collection is arranged in 19 series:
Series I: Origin: Robert College Prior to 1863
Subseries I.1: General
Subseries I.2: Personal Papers of Cyrus Hamlin
Series II: Records of the Trustees
Subseries II. 1: Christopher Robert
Subseries II.2: General
Series III: Records of the President
Subseries III.1: Cyrus Hamlin
Subseries III.2: George Washburn
Subseries III.3: Caleb Gates
Subseries III.4: Monroe, Wright, Black, Ballantine
Subseries III.5: Annual Reports
Series IV: Records of the Vice President, George H. Huntington
Series V: Records of the Dean
Subseries V.1: Edgar Fisher
Subseries V.2: Laurence S. Moore
Subseries V.3: Harold Scott
Subseries V.4: Harold Hazen
Series VI: Records of the Faculty
Series VII: Records of the Students
Series VIII: Records of the Alumni
Series IX: Office of the Trustees, New York
Series X: Financial Records
Series XI: Official College Events
Series XII: Publications
Series XIII: Historical Writings
Series XIV: Oversize Material
Series XV: Photographs
Series XVI: Minutes
Series XVII: Audio Visual
Subseries XVII.1: Films
Subseries XVII.2: Audio Tapes (reel to reel)
Series XVIII: Architectural Plans and Drawings
Series XIX: Microfilms
Addition to the collection. Arranged in 7 series
Series I: Heritage Room/Rare Books (Istanbul)
Series II: Heritage Room/Rare Books (Istanbul & R.C./N.Y. Offices)
Series III: Board of Trustees and Specific Committees
Series IV: Board of Trustees and Financial Documents
Series V: Faculty Lists
Series VI: Education Committee
Series VII: Publications
Subjects
American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey); Robert College (Istanbul, Turkey); Gates, Caleb Frank, 1857-1946.; Hamlin, Cyrus, 1811-1900.; Washburn, George, 1833-1915.; Turkey.; Universities and colleges--Turkey--Istanbul.; College etc., Turkey: Robert College.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Subseries V.1: Edgar Fisher is restricted.
Acquisition
Robert College. Purchase, 2006.
Collection delivered to the Rare Book & Manuscript Library on April 12, 2007
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Origin: Robert College Prior to 1863
  - Subseries I.1: General
    - Correspondence to Christopher Robert from James H. Dwight, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Cyrus Hamlin(?) from Christopher Robert, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from David B. Coe and Milton Badger, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert (includes offer to Hamlin to head the college), 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin (includes a description of objectives of Robert College), 1860 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert, 1860-1861 (Box 1, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 13 to 15)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 16 to 19)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 20 to 23)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin re Morris/ Merriam affair, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin (includes summaries re Morris's role in negotiating with Turkish Government), 1862 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from Robert, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 26 to 28)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 29 to 30)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence to and from Robert, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence to George Perkins and Henry Schauffler from Hamlin, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Perkins, 1861-1865 (Box 1, Folder 33 to 35)
    - Correspondence to Schauffler from Robert, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Schauffler (comments on Chernaud problem as well as policy matters), 1858-1865 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Schauffler, Perkins, Hamlin correspondence to trustees re Chernaud affair, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 38 to 39)
    - Statements about the college plus endorsements from Americans in Turkey; letters of support for the college, 1860, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Historic Statement of the Origin of the Proposed College" written by Hamlin, 1861 or 1862 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence re land acquisition, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Printed version of Robert College's objectives: translation of an article appearing in a French newspaper, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence to Robert re purchase of equipment, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Rufus Anderson and William(?) Goodell, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Copy of documents relating to the establishment of an American College in Istanbul, 1862-1863 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Letter to the Honorable E. Joy Morris from Hamlin, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Petitions for permission to build the college, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence includes letters re negotiations for land acquisition, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence re negotiations for land, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Copy of documents sent to Secretary of State Seward re claims of college against the Turkish Government, [1862] (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Letter to Robert re Hamlin's conduct over Reverend Merriam's murder (written by James Clarke of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions), 1863 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Official letters to Robert re Reverend Merriam's murder, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence to Reverend David B. Coe from A.L. Chapin (President of Beloit College), 1863 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Letter to [Hamlin] from Samuel Morse, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Financial statements (include expenses for the first college year), 1860- 1864 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Narrative of the origin of Robert College prepared by [undated] Robert (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Letter from Hamlin to "Saicus" of the Levant Herald [undated] (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Subseries I.2: The Personal Papers of Cyrus Hamlin
    - Hamlin, sermons, 1837-1896 (Box 3, Folder 1 to 9)
    - Hamlin, lectures, 1834, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Hamlin, minute book of visits among the Irish, 1836-1847 and travels in Turkey as teacher and missionary, 1840-1846 (more detailed than the accounts in My Life and Times) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hamlin, records of seminary at Bebek, 1840s-1850s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Hamlin, letter to his children, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Memo on visits to cholera patients, 1860s (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin from his brother Hannibal Hamlin, 1859- 1862 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence to Hamlin, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hamlin, family correspondence, early 1860s (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Mary Hamlin, notes, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Account of a memorial service for "Susie", [undated] (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series II: Records of the Trustees
  - Subseries II. 1: Christopher Robert
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1864-1867 (Box 4, Folder 1 to 9)
    - Hamlin memo on the presidency of the college, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hamlin memo on printing a catalog of RC, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Hamlin memo on the Corliss Fund, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1868-1875 (Box 4, Folder 13 to 35)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Hamlin, 1876-1878 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Edward North (after Robert's death in 1878 North wrote to Coe and Washburn), 1865-1883 (Box 4, Folder 43 to 49)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Luther Ostrander, 1865-1867 (Box 4, Folder 50 to 51)
    - Correspondence to Robert from John A. Paine, 1866-1867 (Box 4, Folder 52 to 53)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Edwin A. Grosvenor, 1874-1877 (Box 4, Folder 54 to 55)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Alexander Van Millingen, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Albert Long, 1873-1874 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Long, 1876-1878 (Box 4, Folder 58 to 63)
    - Correspondence to Robert from George Washburn, 1867-1878 (Folder 99 contains letter from Washburn to Mrs. Robert re. her husband's death) (Box 6, Folder 64 to 100)
    - Correspondence to Robert from James Gordon (treasurer, Missionary House) re purchase of books, 1861-1864 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - General Correspondence to Robert re purchase of books 1864-1866 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Correspondence to Robert re filing of Certificate of 1864 Incorporation (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Correspondence to Robert re faculty positions 1864-1865 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Langdon Ward, treasurer of The American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1886 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - General correspondence to Robert 1867-1868 (Box 7, Folder 106 to 107)
    - Correspondence to Robert from William Clarke 1868-1869 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Samuel D. Wilcox 1869 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - General correspondence to Robert 1869 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - General correspondence to Robert about construction, equipment and administrative matters, 1869 (Box 7, Folder 111 to 112)
    - General correspondence to Robert 1871-1875 (Box 7, Folder 113 to 128)
    - General correspondence to Robert, 1876-1878 (Box 8, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Correspondence to Robert from M. Hamlin, 1873-1877 (Box 8, Folder 6 to 8)
    - Correspondence to Robert from Henrietta L. Washburn, 1874 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence to C.H. Merriman from Hamlin, 1878-1880 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - General correspondence to Merriman, 1875-1880 (Box 8, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Correspondence to Merriman from Washburn, 1878-1884 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence to Merriman from Long and others, 1881-1883 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - General correspondence to Merriman, 1884-1886 (Box 8, Folder 15 to 17)